Chapter 79.
The prairie.
To scan the lines of his face, or feel the bumps on the head of this Leviathan,
this is a thing which no physioamist or phronologist has as yet undertaken. Such
an enterprise would seem almost as hopeful as for Laviter to have
scrutinized the wrinkles on the rock of Gibralar, or for Gaul to have mounted a
ladder and manipulated the dome of the Pantheon. Still in that famous work of
his, Laviter not only treats of the various faces of men, but also
attentively studies the faces of horses, birds, serpents, and fish, and dwells in
detail upon the modifications of expression discernable therein. Nor have
Gaul and his disciple Spertzheim failed to throw out some hints touching the
phenological characteristics of other beings than man. Therefore, though I am
but illqualified for a pioneer in the application of these two semi-sciences
to the whale, I will do my endeavor. I try all things. I achieve what I can.
Physiomically regarded, the sperm whale is an anomalous creature. He has no
proper nose, and since the nose is the central and most conspicuous of the
features, and since it perhaps most modifies and finally controls their
combined expression, hence it would seem that its entire absence as an external
appendage must very largely affect the countenance of the whale. For as in
landscape gardening, a spire, capola, monument, or tower of some sort is
deemed almost indispensable to the completion of the scene. So no face can
be physinomically in keeping without the elevated openwork belfry of the nose.
Dash the nose from Fidius's marble job, and what a sorry remainder.
Nevertheless, Leviathan is of so mighty a magnitude, all his proportions are so
stately that the same deficiency which in the sculptured Jove were hideous in
him is no blemish at all. Nay, it is an added grandeur. A nose to the whale
would have been impertinent.
As on your physomical voyage you sail round his vast head in your jollyboat,
your noble conceptions of him are never insulted by the reflection that he has a
nose to be pulled, a pestilent conceit which so often will insist upon
obtruding even when beholding the mightiest royal beetle on his throne.
In some particulars, perhaps the most imposing physiomical view to be had of
the sperm whale is that of the full front of his head. This aspect is sublime.
In thought, a fine human brow is like the east when troubled with the morning.
In the repose of the pasture, the curled brow of the bull has a touch of the
grand in it. Pushing heavy cannon up mountain defiles, the elephant's brow is
majestic. human or animal, the mystical brow is as that great golden seal
affixed by the German emperors to their decrees. It signifies God done this day
by my hand. But in most creatures, nay in man himself, very often the brow is
but a mere strip of alpine land lying along the snow line. Few are the
foreheads which like Shakespeare's or melanthons rise so high and descend so
low that the eyes themselves seem clear eternal tideless mountain lakes and all
above them in the foreheads wrinkles you seem to track the antler thoughts
descending there to drink as the highland hunters track the snowprints of
the deer. But in the great sperm whale, this high and mighty godlike dignity
inherent in the brow is so immensely amplified that gazing on it in that full
front view, you feel the deity and the dread powers more forcibly than in
beholding any other object of living nature. For you see no one point
precisely, not one distinct feature is revealed. No, eyes, ears, or mouth, no
face. He has none proper, nothing but that one broad firmament of a forehead
pleaded with riddles dumbly lowering with the doom of boats and ships and
men. Nor in profile does this wondrous brow diminish. Though that way viewed
its grandeur does not doineer upon you so. In profile, you plainly perceive
that horizontal semicroentic depression in the forehead's middle, which in man
is Lavitar's mark of genius.
But how? Genius in the sperm whale. Has the sperm whale ever written a book,
spoken a speech? No. His great genius is declared in his doing nothing particular
to prove it. It is moreover declared in his pyramidical silence. And this
reminds me that had the great sperm whale been known to the young orient
world, he would have been deified by their child magian thoughts. They
deified the crocodile of the Nile because the crocodile is tongueless, and
the sperm whale has no tongue, or at least it is so exceedingly small as to
be incapable of protrusion. If hereafter any highly cultured poetical nation
shall lure back to their birthright the merry Mayday gods of old and livingly
enthrone them again in the now egotistical sky in the now unhaunted
hill then be sure exalted to Job's high seat the great sperm whale shall lord it.
Champolon deciphered the wrinkled granite hieroglyphics. But there is no
Champolon to decipher the Egypt of every man's and every being's face.
Physioammy, like every other human science, is but a passing fable. If
then, Sir William Jones, who read in 30 languages, could not read the simplest
peasants face in its profounder and more subtle meanings, how may unlettered
Ishmael hope to read the awful cali of the sperm whale's brow? I but put that
brow before you. Read it if you can.